<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-06-11T17:21:09+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Being Grateful</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/grateful/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Being Grateful" /><published>2025-01-03T13:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-03T13:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/grateful</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2025/grateful/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="gratitude">Gratitude</h1>
<p>It’s that time of year again when many share their successes from the past year. 
Some have been earned with hard work, some might have been sheer luck. 
When you read the posts on linkedin, you might not be able to tell the difference.
Additionally, failures are rarely ever shared. 
Let’s pause.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
  

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/blog/winter_window_sunrise.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" title="colorful winter sunrise seen through a window" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

</div>

<h2 id="just-be-here">Just be here</h2>

<p>Some time ago, I embarked on a journey of mindfulness and gratitude, and I’ve come to realize it’s not a destination — it’s a continuous process. And that’s the point: enjoying the ride.</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">"People often say that motivation doesn’t last. Well, neither does bathing, that’s why we recommend it daily." - Zig Ziglar</code></p>

<p>Many of us rush through our days, often forgetting to pause and appreciate the present moment. I’m guilty of this more often than I’d like to admit. 
Finding a balance between distraction and focus is challenging. 
I believe there’s no clear black-and-white distinction; instead, we navigate on a scale of shades of gray between distraction and focus.</p>

<ul>
  <li>On one end, distractions can pull us in many directions at a time, leaving us scattered and unproductive. Sometimes, distractions offer a sweet escape from the daily grind.</li>
  <li>On the other, hyper-fixation can consume us so fully that we lose track of time and perspective, while immersing ourself in a productive flow state.</li>
</ul>

<p>However, both states share one drawback: time slips away unnoticed, and the simple, everyday moments fade into the background. 
Let’s pause and observe our surroundings. Look at what we take for granted too often, and appreciate what we have for just a moment.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-take-for-granted-too-often">What I take for granted too often</h2>

<p>There are many things which we tend to forget too easily in our daily life. 
I want to share an incomplete list of things with you, which many people in my social bubble often take for granted, myself included.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>I never experienced war. I was fortunate enough to be born in a country which was not affected by war within my life time. I won the birth lottery!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I never experienced my house burning down or being flooded or losing all my possessions in any other way. I always had a roof over my head or a place to sleep (excluding a few unusual travel experiences).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I never experienced a life-threatening illness. I am (mostly) healthy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I never experienced hunger for long. I always got food eventually.
In fact I can go to a supermarket close to me and buy whatever food I like. 
This is a luxury, which I did not always have. Especially during my studies I had to make careful choices to make the most of the money which I had.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I feel privileged that I like my job, and can make a living with it.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Today, I got to experience some sun, and enjoy a nice cup of coffee with my loved ones. I am grateful for those moments which make me feel truly rich.</p>

<h2 id="to-you">To You</h2>

<p>If you are reading this, than we share at least one thing: 
Our track record of making it through shitty days is 100%. Be proud. 
If you did not achieve something you consider “great” within the last year, be reminded that sometimes surviving is enough. Be gracious. Be your own true best friend.</p>

<p>As we step into the new year, take a moment to appreciate how far you’ve come. Celebrate your resilience, enjoy the little things, and remember — you got this.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Personal" /><category term="Reflections" /><category term="mental health" /><category term="mindset" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Personal reflections about being grateful and pausing.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/img/blog/winter_window_sunrise.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/img/blog/winter_window_sunrise.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How I create scientific posters</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/poster/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I create scientific posters" /><published>2024-10-25T20:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-25T20:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/poster</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/poster/"><![CDATA[<p>You have to prepare a scientific poster and don’t know where to start?</p>

<p>Here I describe my approach in creating posters for conferences and scientific meetings based on an already written publication or article.</p>

<p>Aim at creating a concise storyline. 
Do not put too much on the poster. 
As a presenter you are supposed to be next to the poster, hence provide a visual guide.I recommend to consider it more a conversation starter than a complete summary of your work.</p>

<h2 id="step-by-step-guide">Step-by-step Guide</h2>

<p>Without focussing too much on the content itself, do the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    Verify poster size requirements.
  </li>
  <li>
    Set up a poster template PowerPoint including setting the size appropriately. This provides an empty digital canvas.
    <p>When setting up the template in PowerPoint, it is crucial to select the correct size. You can adjust the slide size under the tab "Design", under "Custom Slide Size", as you can see in the following screenshots:</p>
    <div class="row">
      <div class="col-sm mt-2 mt-md-0">
          

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/2024_10_25_poster/screenshot_pptx01b.png/" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="200%" height="auto" title="powerpoint screenshot" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

      </div>
      <div class="col-sm mt-2 mt-md-0">
          

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/2024_10_25_poster/screenshot_pptx02.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="60%" height="auto" title="powerpoint screenshot submenu" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

      </div>
    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    Print the publication in color one-page layout.
  </li>
  <li>
    Distribute the single pages in a space (floor, whiteboard, ...).
  </li>
  <li>
    Cut out parts of the paper, i.e., figures, tables, paragraphs.
  </li>
  <li>
    Re-arrange parts on a big surface of choice (floor, table, whiteboard with magnets) until the layout is finished.
    <div style="text-align: center;">
      

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/2024_10_25_poster/floor3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" title="pieces on the floor" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

    </div>
  </li>
  <li>
    Arrange elements in PowerPoint accordingly.
  </li>
  <li>
    Collect feedback from people of your choice.
  </li>
  <li>
    Rinse and repeat. Stop when you are satisfied. Avoid infinite loops ;)
  </li>
</ol>
<p>Here is one example of a poster which I created for a conference:</p>
<div style="text-align: center;">
  

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/2024_10_25_poster/2024_05_fg_poster.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" title="final conference poster" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

</div>

<h2 id="reflection-and-comments">Reflection and comments</h2>
<p>You might wonder why I use PowerPoint if the paper is written with LaTeX. 
In fact in the past during my PhD I used LaTeX, but found PowerPoint more flexible, because:</p>
<ol>
  <li>It is WYSIWYG (what you see is what you get).</li>
  <li>I like to move pictures, and textboxes freely by hand. I feel that this approach gives me more flexibility and less troubles than LaTeX.</li>
  <li>Equations: In the past I used LaTeX for posters specifically because it was easier to write equations. However, since I discovered the plugin IguanaTex for PowerPoint, this sealed the deal for me.</li>
</ol>

<p>In conclusion: PowerPoint might not the best tool for posters in general, but it works for me.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Research" /><category term="&amp;" /><category term="Knowledge" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My approach on creating posters for conferences and research events.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tools which make your life easier</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/tools/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tools which make your life easier" /><published>2024-06-17T20:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-17T20:30:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/tools</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2024/tools/"><![CDATA[<p>Beyond the common and most frequent suggestion “ChatGPT”, there are so many tools out there which can make your (work) life so much easier!</p>

<h2 id="latex-and-powerpoint---the-best-of-both-worlds">LaTeX and Powerpoint - The best of both worlds</h2>

<p>To create presentations most people use either Powerpoint or LaTeX. 
Both have their benefits, and clearly you should select what works best for you. 
Here are my thoughts:</p>
<ul>
  <li>I like PowerPoint for presentations with many visuals, because I can intuitively create graphs, and freely move images and videos on the slide, and it just works (most of the time). However, adding equations has always been a bit painful.</li>
  <li>I like LaTeX for academic writing, and presentations with many equations. It allows me to conveniently write equations in a nice and straight-forward manner. However, placing images a certain way, and using animations and videos remains a challenge.</li>
</ul>

<p>It turns out there is tool which allows you to combine the best of both worlds! 
The add-on <a href="https://www.jonathanleroux.org/software/iguanatex/">IguanaTex</a> allows you to incorporate LaTeX equations which are being rendered nicely.</p>

<h2 id="collaborative-academic-writing">Collaborative Academic Writing</h2>

<p>Especially when writing a scientific report with several people, you might benefit greatly from <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/">overleaf</a>.</p>

<h2 id="simplify-your-literature-collection">Simplify your Literature Collection</h2>

<p>In the past many researchers struggled with a big pile of research papers. The digitalization offers more convenient solutions! 
For many that meant a folder full of research papers in pdf format.</p>

<p>But here is more! My life got a lot easier when I discovered literature management programs. Obviously there are more than one. 
My tool of choice became <a href="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</a> which is 
“a free, easy-to-use tool to help you collect, organize, annotate, cite, and share research.”</p>

<p>Why do I like it?</p>
<ul>
  <li>It is open source. (Main reason why I prefer it over mendeley.)</li>
  <li>You can create collections, annotate, and share. It allows collaboration.</li>
  <li>Collect with one click: <a href="https://www.zotero.org/download/connectors">Plugins for your browser</a> allow a direct import of literature from webpages via one click. It creates a bibtex entry, and downloads the pdf automatically - if it is available.</li>
  <li>My favourite recent discovery: You can directly import citations from your zotero into <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/">overleaf</a>! Read <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/learn/how-to/How_to_link_your_Overleaf_account_to_Mendeley_and_Zotero">here</a> how to do it.</li>
</ul>

<p>Drawbacks:
For one reference the retrieved bibtex might differ depending on the website of choice. This should be taken into account especially when using arxiv. If you retrieve the information from this page, you might miss that the paper was officially published in a peer-reviewed venue.</p>

<h2 id="more-to-come">More to come</h2>
<p>There is more to come. 
I would be thrilled to receive input on your favourite tools.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Productivity" /><category term="&amp;" /><category term="Tools" /><category term="software" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a growing list of tools which I find helpful.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">René’s PhD defense</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/rene_defense/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="René’s PhD defense" /><published>2023-11-24T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-24T20:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/rene_defense</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2023/rene_defense/"><![CDATA[<p>Today was the <a href="https://en.itu.dk/Research/PhD-Programme/PhD-Defences/PhD-Defences-2023/November/Rene-Haas">defense</a> of the very first PhD student I had the pleasure to officially co-supervise: René Haas. I could not be prouder. Shortly, after I started working at ITU 2019 we started working together with Sami S. Brandt, on a research project titled <em>Synthesis of Face Images Using Generative Algorithms</em>. This project was then extended into a Master thesis <em>Exploring the latent space of StyleGAN for semantic face editing and expression transfer</em>. 
This lead to a proposal for a PhD project, which got accepted, and the rest is history!</p>

<p>And finally today René defended his thesis with the title <em>Deep Generative Models for Faces and Expressions</em> with great success. 
A big thank you also to the committee members <a href="https://veronikach.com/">Veronika Cheplygina</a>, <a href="https://fredkahl.github.io/">Fredrik Kahl</a>, and <a href="https://users.aalto.fi/~laines9/">Samuli Laine</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academic" /><category term="Life" /><category term="PhD" /><category term="achievements" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Impressions from my first PhD defense on the other side.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mathias’ Best Paper Award</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/mathias_award/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mathias’ Best Paper Award" /><published>2022-03-24T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-24T20:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/mathias_award</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/mathias_award/"><![CDATA[<p>It does not happen so often that the work of our students get’s submitted to a conference. This time, not only was the work of Mathias submitted to a conference, it was also accepted for publication, and received the best student paper award! 
Congratulations to Mathias’ for this great achievement!</p>

<!--[assets/img/2022_03_award_mathias.png]-->

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/2022_03_award_mathias.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="80%" height="auto" title="Mathias (middle) with his supervisors Stella (left) and Sami (right)" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

<!--The corresponding paper 
"Neural Network-based Human Motion Smoother", Mathias Bastholm , Stella Graßhof, and Sami Brandt, In the International Conference on Pattern Recognition Applications and Methods (ICPRAM), Feb 2022 -->

<h1 id="references">References</h1>
<div class="publications">
  <h2 class="bibliography">2022</h2>
<ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row">
  
    <div class="col-sm-2 preview">
      
        
          
          

<figure>
  <picture>
    <!-- Auto scaling with imagemagick -->
    <!--
      See https://www.debugbear.com/blog/responsive-images#w-descriptors-and-the-sizes-attribute and
      https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/HTML/Multimedia_and_embedding/Responsive_images for info on defining 'sizes' for responsive images
    -->
    
    <img src="/assets/img/publication_preview/2022_bastholm_icpram.gif" class="preview z-depth-1 rounded" width="100%" height="auto" alt="2022_bastholm_icpram.gif" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />
  </picture>

  
</figure>

        
      
    </div>
  

  <!-- Entry bib key -->
  <div id="bastholm_neural_2022" class="col-sm-8">
    <!-- Title -->
    <div class="title">Neural Network-based Human Motion Smoother</div>
    <!-- Author -->
    <div class="author">
      

      
      Mathias
            Bastholm
          ,&nbsp;<em>Stella
            Graßhof</em>,&nbsp;and&nbsp;Sami
            Brandt
          
    </div>

    <!-- Journal/Book title and date -->
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    <div class="periodical">
      <em>In the International Conference on Pattern Recognition Applications and Methods (ICPRAM)</em> ,  Feb 2022
    </div>
    <div class="periodical">
      
    </div>

    <!-- Links/Buttons -->
    <div class="links">
      
        <a class="abstract btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">Abs</a>
      
      
      
      
      
        
          <a href="/assets/pdf/2022_bastholm_icpram.pdf" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">PDF</a>
        
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
    </div>
    
      
      
      
      
    

    
      <!-- Hidden abstract block -->
      <div class="abstract hidden">
        <p>Recording real life human motion as a skinned mesh animation with an acceptable quality is usually difficult. Even though recent advances in pose estimation have enabled motion capture from off-the-shelf webcams, the low quality makes it infeasible for use in production quality animation. This work proposes to use recent advances in the prediction of human motion through neural networks to augment low quality human motion, in an effort to bridge the gap between cheap recording methods and high quality recording. First, a model, competitive with prior work in short-term human motion prediction, is constructed. Then, the model is trained to clean up motion from two low quality input sources, mimicking a real world scenario of recording human motion through two webcams. Experiments on simulated data show that the model is capable of significantly reducing noise, and it opens the way for future work to test the model on annotated data.</p>
      </div>
    

    

    
  </div>
</div>
</li></ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Academic" /><category term="Life" /><category term="achievements" /><category term="conferences" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few words about Mathias Achievement]]></summary></entry></feed>